Finding Aid for Michigan Historic Preservation Network Records, 1980-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Historic Preservation Network Records 1980-2004
Michigan Historic Preservation Network.
(in 17 boxes)
9 linear feet
0519 Bp 2
Statewide organization established in part to create an awareness of Michigan's cultural heritage and architectural history and to encourage the preservation and stewardship of important state historic resources. Records document the administration and programs of the Network, including conferences, publications, training sessions, and awards given for local preservation achievements.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited by the organization in January 2005 (donor no. 9555 ).
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Historic Preservation Network is the largest membership organization in the state dedicated to recognizing and preserving Michigan's rich cultural and architectural heritage. Membership includes owners of residential, commercial, industrial, institutional and agricultural property; students and educators; governmental officials and appointees; archaeologists, architects and designers; landscape architects and landscapers; interior designers, contractors, developers, realtors, bankers and insurance agents; and preservation volunteers and professionals. The volunteer board of directors and staff help Network members maintain the neighborhoods where they live and the downtowns where they work, build new in ways that respect and reinforce local character, revitalize some of Michigan's oldest urban centers, adapt all types of buildings for current uses and use to best advantage the rich rural, agricultural and maritime heritage of Michigan.
The founders saw a need for a nonprofit organization that fostered the protection of the state's irreplaceable historic buildings, structures, sites, objects, features and open spaces. They saw the benefits of informing others that these were community assets appropriate for continued use or creative adaptive reuse. They wanted to give recognition to successful preservation projects and coordinate and publicize efforts across the state. Most of all, they wanted to share their experience and expertise with others.
On May 30, 1981, members of the Detroit Historic District Commission convened a meeting of fellow commissioners from around Michigan. Seeing that they had much to learn from each other, the more than 50 people who gathered that day at historic Fort Wayne decided to continue meeting. The group met on again on June 18, 1981, to develop bylaws, find dollars for a budget, establish a newsletter, and assign responsibilities for the work at hand. They chose the name "Michigan Historic District Network" to reflect their objectives to provide commissioner education, serve as an information clearinghouse, lobby for stronger state enabling legislation for local historic district ordinances, and market a compelling preservation message. Staff from Michigan's State Historic Preservation Office were on hand in Detroit, establishing from the start a close working relationship with the Network in support of its objectives.
Monroe hosted the first statewide conference that October. There, the first of the objectives was tackled: strengthening Public Act 169 (1970) to allow commissions design review over both historic and non-historic resources in historic districts.
The fledgling group soon felt overwhelmed, however, and, after the 2nd Annual Statewide Conference was hosted by Livonia in May of 1982, its efforts languished. The Network's leaders held an "emergency meeting" that fall at the historic Holly Hotel the decision was made to concentrate on education and legislation.
To conserve funds and volunteer energy, the Network piggybacked its 1983 spring conference with Wayne State University's Local History Conference. Nellie Longsworth of Preservation Action came to this initial Wayne State gathering and advised the Network on how to amend PA 169. A single-topic fall workshop then was held in the Lansing offices of the State Historic Preservation Office. This schedule of biannual meetings continued through 1986, with volunteers thus able to focus on getting PA 169 amended. Governor James Blanchard signed the amendment into law on October 1, 1986, giving commissions the right of review over all district resources.
The Network had seven years of solid programming under its belt when, with assistance from the National Trust for Historic Preservation, four "Forums" were hosted to determine Michigan's preservation needs at the close of its Sesquicentennial Year of 1987. Gathering in Grand Rapids, Durand, Marquette, and Traverse City from late 1988 to early 1989, Forum participants asked that the Network promote further strengthening of PA 169, assist with new local protective ordinances, serve as an information exchange, develop training programs, and advocate for local and state preservation efforts. In response to these objectives, the Network -- now renamed the Michigan Historic Preservation Network to reflect its expanding audience -- initiated intensive Commissioner Training Workshops in 1989, filed for incorporation that same year, secured 501(c)(3) not-for-profit status in the Fall of 1990, worked with the SHPO on their first collaborative Fall workshop in 1991, and succeeded with sweeping amendments to Public Act 169 signed into law by Gov. John M. Engler in 1992.
The Network hosted the National Trust's Midwest Regional Meeting as part of the 1993 statewide conference in Kalamazoo. By the summer of 1994, the Network had become one of seven statewide organizations competitively selected for the Trust's Statewides Initiative Program. The Initiative offered help to statewides that had no paid staff but were in a position to expand services if staff were added. When later that year the Network became one of four statewides awarded matching Trust funds, the $35,000 received allowed Jennifer Radcliff, longtime elected head of the Network, to be hired. With Jennifer on board, the Network soon implemented its first 3-year plan, its first blueprint for fundraising, and a program-driven budget.
The Network expanded programming in 1995. The statewide conference in Muskegon was the first to have sponsors and to earn a much-needed surplus to help cover salary. The Michigan Humanities Council provided funding for six barn rehabilitation workshops co-sponsored by the Network and MSU Extension. Network participation with the Detroit Heritage and Community Development Forum continued. Looking for a way to attract new members as well as fund an increased operations budget, the Network launched an Annual Fall Benefit Evening.
In 1996 the pace quickened. The Americana Foundation made a $14,000 grant to produce a video about the Network's efforts, and gave another $13,000 for promotional and membership brochures. The 1996 annual statewide conference in Ann Arbor was a breakthrough, doubling the usual audience, netting over $9,000 in gifts and sponsorships, attracting more than 50 new members, and hosting National Trust president Richard Moe as the keynoter. The Sweetwater Trail officially opened in the fall, promising to attract tourists to the back roads that lead to historic buildings and maritime sites. The first of the regional workshops developed by the Network for its Rural and Small Town Preservation Initiative was held in Boyne City, as was the 1st Annual Michigan African American Symposium with the Network as a co-sponsor.
The Construction Trades Council formally got underway in the spring of 1998. It has since become the arm of the Network bringing together trades people, contractors, design professionals, and owners of historic properties to study "lost" techniques of historic construction and present-day preservation practice. In April of 1998, the Network joined with the Michigan Historical Center and others to create the Michigan Lighthouse Project, a landmark effort to promote the transfer of over 70 Michigan lighthouses from the U.S. Coast Guard to local groups and private individuals.
January 1, 1999, witnessed the kickoff of a 25% state investment tax credit signed into law by Governor John M. Engler to benefit owners restoring historic properties in locally designated historic districts. A series of tax act workshops spread the word and has resulted in the first 70 applications for preservation projects. In the summer of 1999, the 1st Annual Fayette Field School, held in the UP's Fayette State Park, provided students academic credit and hands-on training in preservation technology and conservation. And on the 1st of December, the Network met a goal it thought it never would reach: the leasing of real office space in a historic Henry Ford cottage industries building in Clarkston. It all was reported on the Network's new web site online by year-end.
These records were assembled and processed in 2004 in preparation for a conference marking the organization's 25th anniversary. The records are organized in five series corresponding to the creators of the records.
Subjects:
Michigan Historic Preservation Network.; Historic preservation--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Belle Isle (Detroit, Mich.); Corktown (Detroit, Mich.); University of Michigan. Detroit Observatory.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; Libraries--Michigan--Detroit.; Libraries--Michigan--Saginaw.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Detroit (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.
Genre Terms:
Compact discs.; Photographs.
- Treasurer Records 1980-circa 2000
  Treasurer Records includes files kept by Louisa Pieper, the treasurer of MHPN. Subjects include meetings, workshops and conferences; board minutes, bylaws and handouts; incorporation papers; membership records; state legislation; budgets and fiscal records; and correspondence. These records are particularly useful in documenting the early history of the organization.
  - Meetings and workshops 1980-1984 (Box 1)
  - Board minutes and information 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Board minutes and information 1989 (Box 1)
  - Board and committee minutes and information 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - Board and committee minutes and information 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1981-1990 (Box 1)
  - Nonprofit status and incorporation 1981-1990 (Box 1)
  - Membership lists and recruitment 1984-1992 (Box 2)
  - Membership lists and recruitment 1994-1998 (Box 2)
  - Membership, reports, renewals and dues 1992-1998 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1981-1992 (Box 2)
  - Meeting handouts, ca. 1980-1984 (Box 2)
  - Network meetings, workshops and conferences 1984-1994
    - Ypsilanti September 1984 (Box 2)
    - Detroit April 1985 (Box 2)
    - Grand Rapids August 1985 (Box 2)
    - Flint November 1985 (Box 2)
    - Muskegon November 1986 (Box 2)
    - East Lansing May 1987 (Box 2)
    - Kalamazoo October 1987 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor May 1988 (Box 3)
    - Detroit September, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Traverse City May 1989 (Box 3)
    - Lansing October 1989 (Box 3)
    - Farmington Hills May 1990 (Box 3)
    - Marshall October 1990 (Box 3)
    - Port Huron May 1991 (Box 3)
    - Petoskey September 1991 (Box 3)
    - Grand Rapids May 1992 (Box 3)
    - Sault Ste. Marie September 1992 (Box 3)
    - Marquette September 1993 (Box 3)
    - Bloomfield Hills May 1994 (Box 3)
  - Network board retreat September 1989 (Box 3)
  - Historic preservation issues forums 1989 (Box 3)
  - National Trust Midwest Conference, Kalamazoo April 1993 (Box 3)
  - Network graphics (logo) (Box 3)
  - Network newsletters
    - Correspondence about 1982-1999 (Box 4)
    - Issues of newsletter
      - 1982-1993 (Box 4)
      - 1994-1999 (Box 4)
  - Legislation, Michigan 1981-1986 (Box 4)
  - Legislation, Michigan 1987-1991 (Box 4)
  - Legislative task force, committee
    - General 1991-1996 (Box 4)
    - Notices 1991-1996 (Box 4)
    - Notes 1991-1996 (Box 4)
    - Reports 1991-1993 (Box 4)
  - Legislation (various)
    - Legislative task force, lobbying 1991-1994 (Box 5)
    - Legislative task force, lobbying 1995 (Box 5)
    - Advocacy and communication 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Amending PA 169 1990-1992 (Box 5)
    - Matheiu-Gast Act (Box 5)
    - Fiscal documents and correspondence 1983-1991 (Box 5)
    - Fiscal documents and correspondence 1992-1996 (Box 5)
    - Budgets, reports and statements 1989-1993, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Budgets, reports and statements 1994-1997, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Tax returns and exemption 1988-1996 (Box 6)
  - Charitable trust and solicitation license 1993-1995 (Box 6)
  - Challenge grant, endowment and contributions 1995-1998 (Box 6)
- Editor Records, ca. 1996-2004
  Editor Records consists of records kept by Janine Saputo, editor of the MHPN Newsletter. Subject headings include newsletters; awards; meetings, workshops and conferences; materials and publications; and MHPN history. This series is useful in studying the period of time it covers, especially the early award winners and newsletters of this time period.
  - Newsletters, "Network News" 1996-2004, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Newsletter production files 2002-2003, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Newsletter production files 2003-2004, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - General newsletter information 2003 (Box 8)
  - Network printed materials and publications 1993-2002 (Box 8)
  - Biographical information 1995-1999 (Box 8)
  - Membership lists 1993-1999 (Box 8)
  - MHPN history narrative 2001-2003 (Box 8)
  - Network meetings, workshops and conferences 1990-2003
    - Marshall October 1990 (Box 9)
    - Detroit April 2001 (Box 9)
    - Traverse City April 2002 (Box 9)
    - Sault Ste. Marie September 2002 (Box 9)
    - Kalamazoo/Battle Creek April 2003 (Box 9)
  - Awards 2001-2004, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - MHPN Technical Report October 2002 (Box 9)
  - Colorado preservation booklet 2002 (Box 9)
- Janet Kreger Records
  The Janet Kreger Records series consists of records kept by Kreger, a founding member, board member and board president of MHPN. Subjects include Investment Tax Credit legislation, strategic planning, and National Trust Statewides Initiatives grant materials. Among other things, this series provides exclusive evidence of the planning and actions of the organization during the 1990s and beyond.
  - Investment Tax Credit, legislation 1992-1995 (Box 10)
  - Investment Tax Credit, legislation 1996-1997 (Box 10)
  - Investment Tax Credit, legislation 1998-1999 (Box 10)
  - Investment Tax Credit, Implementation and regulations 1994-2001 (Box 10)
  - Statewide Initiatives 1995-1997 (Box 11)
  - Investment Tax Credit, National Trust challenge grant--working copy 1994 (Box 11)
  - Investment Tax Credit, National Trust challenge grant--"spare copy" 1994 (Box 11)
  - Strategic planning, materials 1994 (Box 11)
  - Strategic planning, Action plans 1998-2004 (Box 11)
- Administrative Office Records
  Administrative Office Records includes award submissions, winners, correspondence, history, and nomination ideas; and fiscal records. This series also includes a significant number of photographs (in print and electronic format) of preservation activities across Michigan. The awards submissions are especially valuable as they depict preservation activities be carried out by different segments of the population across Michigan. The photographs in this series exist in many formats, including film negatives, slides, prints, and electronic, and usually include descriptions of the scenes they depict.
  - Awards
    - General information 1992-2000 (Box 12)
    - Annual awards 1994-1999, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - Non-winners 1999 (Box 12)
    - Winners 1999 (Box 12)
    - Submissions, commercial, Hoyt Library, Saginaw, Michigan 1999 (Box 12)
    - Submissions, commercial, Lapeer post office 1999 (Box 12)
    - Submissions, community, Preservation Wayne 1999 (Box 12)
    - Submissions, government/institution, Michigan stove 1999 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, Martha Cook Building; 1999 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, government/institution, St. Joseph County Courthouse 1999 (Box 13)
    - Annual awards 2000 (Box 13)
    - Awards ceremony 2000 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, commercial, Frauenthal Center, Muskegon 2000 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, commercial, Garfield Building 2000 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, commercial, Schmidt Pharmacy 2000 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, citizen, Pete Sandman 2000 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, citizen, Howard Taylor 2000 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, government/institution, Detroit Observatory 2000 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, government/institution, City of Ypsilanti 2000 (Box 13)
    - Submissions, building, Eustace-Cole Hall 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Schlenker Building 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Crazy Wisdom Bookstore 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Lane Hall 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Cathedral of St. Andrew 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Wealthy Theater, Grand Rapids 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Berkey & Gay Building 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Grosse Pointe Log Cabin 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Hereford & Hops 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Cross Street Village 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, building, Cottages at Grand Traverse Pavilions 2001 (Box 14)
    - Submissions, government/institution, Fair Lane 2001 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, government/institution, Lane Hall 2001 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, government/institution, St. Joseph County Courthouse 2001 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, government/institution, Chippewa Nature Center 2001 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, community, Washtenaw County Museum 2001 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, community, Wealthy Theater 2001 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, unclassified, Grace Church 2001 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, unclassified, Young Keepers of the Lighthouses 2001 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, Building, Mackinac Island State Park Commission 2002 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, Building, Carpenter Street School Community 2002 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, government/institution, Kalamazoo 2003 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, community, Motorcities: Automotive National Heritage Area 2003 (Box 15)
    - Submissions, cultural landscape, Belle Isle 2003 (Box 16)
    - Submissions, building, Motherhouse Renovation 2003 (Box 16)
    - Submissions, government/institution, Battle Point Cemetery 2003 (Box 16)
    - Submissions, government/institution, Ann Arbor street exhibits 2003 (Box 16)
    - Submissions, Community, Marshall Civic Center Trust 2003 (Box 16)
    - Submissions, Community, Southwest Nonprofit Housing Corp., Detroit 2003 (Box 16)
    - Submissions, Cultural landscape, Cranbrook 2004 (Box 16)
    - Submissions, Building, The Boardwalk Building, Grand Rapids 2004 (Box 16)
    - Submissions, Citizen, William "Tiny" Zehnder 2003 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Citizen, Mike Mort 2003 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, community, Kevin and Amy Banker & Old Town District, Port Huron 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Community, Corktown 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Community, Muskegon 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Building, The Eureka Building, Detroit 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Building, Rose and Robert Skillman Branch Library, Detroit 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Building, Consumer's Energy Post Office, Jackson 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Building, Richard House 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Building, West Hall 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Building, Rochester Hills Museum 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Building, Sharon Mills Park 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Government/institution, HistWeb 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Government/institution, Smith-Flat Rock Hotel 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Citizen, Fred Beal 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Citizen, Mary Asmus 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Tax credit project, Hilzinger Block 2004 (Box 17)
    - Submissions, Cultural landscape, horse fountain 2004 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence 2004 (Box 17)
  - History and nomination ideas 2004 (Box 17)
  - Fiscal documents, IRS & Mich. Dept. of Treasury returns, Len Pytlak copies 1995, 1996, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - MHPN copies 1996 (Box 17)
  - Chart of accounts and financial statements 1996 (Box 17)
  - Bank statements and deposit records 1996 (Box 17)
  - Check register 1996 (Box 17)
  - Financial statements 1997 (Box 17)
  - Bank statements and deposit records 1997 (Box 17)
- Significant Individuals Associated With MHPN
  Included in the series Significant Individuals Associated With MHPN is information about the persons relationship to the Network, such as time span, office held, volunteer duties, award won, and contact information.
  - List of board members, volunteers, staff and award winners, ca. 1980-2004 (Box 17)
  - Ted Ligibel file
    - Board of directors handbook 1998 (Box 17)
    - Annual reports 2002-2004 (Box 17)